Guide to the John Maudgridge Snowden Allison Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Maudgridge Snowden Allison papers
1771-1943
MS 33
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
(19 boxes, 1 folio)
Papers of John Maudgridge Snowden Allison, author and professor of history at Yale University. The papers contain correspondence, teaching materials, and research files, including original letters and documents by French political figures of the 18th and 19th century. Among these are François Guizot, Alphonse Larmartine, King Louis Philippe, Chrétien Malesherbes, and Adolphe Thiers. Also included is a promissory note by Talleyrand and documents signed by Louis XVI. Among his personal correspondents are Léon Allégret, Henri Focillon, Henri Malo, Richard L. Tighe, Chauncey Brewster Tinker, Gilbert M. Troxell, and Henri Peyre. Two-thirds of the papers are made up of teaching materials and include lectures and lecture notes, student papers, card files and essays, articles and reviews on French history. Also included are papers relating to Allison's army service during World War I and extensive correspondence with his mother from his school days through World War I.
Allison, John Maudgridge Snowden, 1888-1944
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Allison estate, 1944.
Biographical / Historical
Author, educator; B.A., Princeton, 1910, M.A., 1912, Ph.D., 1914; instructor and assistant professor in history, Yale, 1914-1926, associate professor, European history, 1926-1929, professor of European history, 1929-1935, Randolph W. Townsend, Jr. Professor, 1935-1944; author of books on French history.
Scope and Contents
Papers of John Maudgridge Snowden Allison, author and professor of history at Yale University. The papers contain correspondence, teaching materials, and research files, including original letters and documents by French political figures of the 18th and 19th century. Among these are François Guizot, Alphonse Larmartine, King Louis Philippe, Chrétien Malesherbes, and Adolphe Thiers. Also included is a promissory note by Talleyrand and documents signed by Louis XVI. Among his personal correspondents are Léon Allégret, Henri Focillon, Henri Malo, Richard L. Tighe, Chauncey Brewster Tinker, Gilbert M. Troxell, and Henri Peyre. Two-thirds of the papers are made up of teaching materials and include lectures and lecture notes, student papers, card files and essays, articles and reviews on French history. Also included are papers relating to Allison's army service during World War I and extensive correspondence with his mother from his school days through World War I.
History -- Study and teaching; Mothers and sons; World War, 1914-1918; Europe; France -- History -- 18th century; France -- History -- 19th century; Educators; Historians; Louis Philippe, King of the French, 1773-1850; Allégret, Léon; Allison, John Maudgridge Snowden, 1888-1944; Focillon, Henri, 1881-1943; Guizot, François, 1787-1874; Larmartine, Alphonse; Malesherbes, Chrétien Guillaume de Lamoignon de, 1721-1794; Malo, Henri, b. 1868; Peyre, Henri, 1901-1988; Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, 1754-1838; Thiers, Adolphe, 1797-1877; Tighe, Richard L.; Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1876-1963; Troxell, Gilbert McCoy, 1893-1967; Brooks School, North Andover, Mass; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History
- Inventory
  - General correspondence
    - Académie des Sciences...d'Aix: ALS, 1923 Oct 18; 2 typed drafts (Box 1)
    - Adam, Charles M.: ALS, 1925 Aug 5 (Box 1)
    - Allégret, Léon: Correspondence, 16 ALS, 1914-1923; cards; clippings (Box 1)
    - Allison, John M. S., Jr.: Correspondence, drafts, a horoscope, certificate as a lay reader. (Box 1)
    - American Church Monthly, Selden P. Delaney, ed.: 3 TLS, 1922-1924 (Box 1)
    - Angell, James Rowland (1869-1949): ALS, 1933 May 29 (Box 1)
    - Armstrong, George Alexander: ALS, 1917 Jul 27 (Box 1)
    - Arnold, Harold Sears (1877-): AL (init.), 1925 Oct 13 (Box 1)
    - Ashburn, Frank Davis (1903-, Yale 1925): ALS, 1925 Jul 1 (Box 1)
    - Babcock, Henry Holmes (1913-, Yale 1935): ALS, 1934 Mar 23 (Box 1)
    - Bates, Robert Chapman (1901-1942, Yale 1923): 2 ALS, 1923 Oct 28 - Nov 10 (Box 1)
    - Becket, George Campbell (1901-, Yale 1923): ANS, Thurs., n.y. (Box 1)
    - Berkeley Divinity School (W.P. Ladd): ANS, Sunday, n.y.; printed program, etc. (incl. MS of address by Allison, "The Return to Antiquity," 1922 Jun) (Box 1)
    - "Betsy, Miss": ALS, 1921 Jun 27 (Box 1)
    - Bontroux, Emile: 2 ANS, 1921 Aug 26 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Thatcher Magoun, Jr. (1908-, Yale 1930): ALS, 1930 Oct 25 (Box 1)
    - Burr, Hudson (1895-, Yale 1918): ALS, n.y. Mar 8 (Box 1)
    - Cahen, L.: ANS, n.d.; with draft (Box 1)
    - "Cari, Aunt": ALS, 1921 Oct 3 (Box 1)
    - Carr, Elmendorf L.: 2 ALS, 1 TLS, 1921-1925 (Box 1)
    - Caudet (?), Revue des Sciences Politiques: TLS, 1925 Jul 25 (Box 1)
    - Chalmers, Andrew Burns, Jr. (1903-, Yale 1925): ALS, 1925 Sep 25 (Box 1)
    - Chapman, "Paddy": ANS, 1921 Aug 24 (Box 1)
    - Chappell, Thomas Huntington (1906-, Yale 1928): 2 ALS, 1928-1933 (Box 1)
    - Chauvenet, William (1896-, Yale 1919): ALS, 1917 Jul 8 (Box 1)
    - Clough, Charles Asa, Jr. (1903-, Yale 1926): Mimeographed carol (Box 1)
    - Converse, Allan Dean, Jr. (1911-, Yale 1933): ALS, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Crosby, John, Jr. (1898-, Yale 1920): ALS, 1920 Jan 2 (Box 1)
    - Dater, Walton Ferguson (1899-, Yale 1922): 2 ALS, Tuesday, n.y.; 1922 Jul 18 (Box 1)
    - Davis, Richard Marden (1912-, Yale 1933): ALS, 1933 Aug 26 (Box 1)
    - de la Lande, May: ALS, 1918 Jun 19 (Box 1)
    - Draper, John Haggerty (1895-1954, Yale 1917): ALS, 1921 Oct 20 (Box 1)
    - Dunham, William Huse, Jr. (1901-, Yale 1923): ALS, 1925 Jun 22 (Box 1)
    - "Eka, Aunt Mamie": 4 ALS, 1918-1922 (Box 1)
    - Elliot-Malden, Henry (Royal Historical Society): ALS, 1921 Sep 10; draft reply (Box 1)
    - Elizabethan Club, [George] Lauder Greenway (Yale 1925, Sec., 1924): ANS, 1924 Nov 11 (Box 1)
    - Enders, Ostrom (1902-, Yale 1925): ALS, 1925 Oct 10 (Box 1)
    - Evans, Madeline: ANS, n.y. Aug 18 (Box 1)
    - Ewing, Jack Sweetser (1901-, Yale 1925): 2 ALS, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Farrand, Max (1869-1945): 2 TLS, 1 ALS, 1919-1925 (Box 1)
    - Gabriel, Ralph Henry (1890-, Yale 1913): TLS, 1926 Nov 8 (Box 1)
    - Gardner, Walter P.: TNS, 1932 Oct 25 (Box 1)
    - General Theological Seminary, New York City: Corresp., 1922; 4 letters (Box 1)
    - George, Alice: ALS, n.y. Oct 16 (Box 1)
    - George, Robert H.: TLS, 1918 Dec 10; ALS, n.y. Aug 24 (Box 1)
    - Gervais, G.: ALS, 1917 Feb 16 (Box 1)
    - Grandon, Frances, The Churchmen's Alliance: ANS, 1921 Nov 1 (Box 1)
    - Green, Thomas Dudley (1902-, Yale 1923): TLS, 1924 May 12 (Box 1)
    - Greenslet, Ferris (1875-1959): 5 TLS, 1925; 2 carbon replies (Box 1)
    - Hall, Francis J.: ALS to Francis B. Roseboro, 1921 Jun 3 (Box 1)
    - Hendrick, Ives (1898-, Yale 1921): TNS, 1921 Jun 29 (Box 1)
    - Henry, William Lester (1874-, Yale 1896): 19 ALS, 1917+; 1 carbon reply (Box 1)
    - Hoye, Wilbur Grant (1897-, Yale 1918): ALS, 1917 Jul 4 (Box 1)
    - Hutchison, Juan Ceballos (1905-, Yale 1928): 2 A cards S; 2 ALS to 1925 (Box 1)
    - Institut Historique et Héraldique de France: TLS, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Jameson, Franklin: TLS, 1923 May 15 (Box 1)
    - Jenckes, David (1912-, Yale 1935): Telegram, 1935 Jun 20, 5 ALS, n.d.; poems; Hist. 32 exam, 1935; varia (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Allen (1870-1931): 2 TLS, 4 ALS, 1919-1924 (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Allen Sheppard (1901-, Yale 1922): ALS, 1922 Jun 20 (Box 1)
    - Jones, Fredrick Scheetz (1866-1944): TLS, 1921 Feb 8 (Box 1)
    - Jones, Walter Clyde, Jr. (1902-, Yale 1925): ALS, 1925 Jul 15 (Box 1)
    - Kellogg, H. S.: TLS, 1924 Feb 4; carbon reply (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Hutton (?): 2 ALS, 1921 Aug 4; 1922 Sep 25 (Box 1)
    - L[aughlin?], L. A.: ALS, n.y. Aug 30 (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, Francis Bailey (d. 1905): 3 ALS, 1858-1905 (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, Francis Bailey, II: 3 ALS, 1 TLS, 1917-1923 (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, George McCully, Jr.: 2 ALS, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, Henry M.: 2 ALS, 1918 May 19; n.d. (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, Margaret (Burtch) (b. 1839): ALS, 1922 Aug 13 (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, William Hamilton: 3 TLS, 12 ALS, 1918+ (with material from Headmaster, etc., of the Donaldson School, the Hoosac School, Princeton Univ., etc.) (Box 1)
    - Lavietes, Edwin B. (i.e. Baruch Edwin Lavietes, 1903-, Yale 1924): ALS, 1924 Oct 14 (Box 1)
    - Leland, Waldo Gifford (1879-): TLS, 1923 Jul 4 (Box 1)
    - MacDill, John Harcourt (1906-, Yale 1927): TMS, 1933: "The Faculty Ballet" (Box 1)
    - Malo, Henri: 5 ALS, 1921-1925 (Box 1)
    - Malone, Dumas (1892-): TLS, 1923 Oct 1 (Box 1)
    - Marsh, Ralph Thayer (1897-, Yale 1921) ALS, 1920 Jun 20; card, 1921 Aug 26 (Box 1)
    - Mendell, Clarence Whittlesey (1883-, Yale 1904): ANS, 1922 Jun 10 (Box 1)
    - Milmine, George Parsons (1901-, Yale 1923): ALS, 1922 Jun 13 (Box 1)
    - Mitchell, Leonel E. W.: ALS, 1923 Nov 16 (Box 1)
    - Mongan, Gorton P.: ALS, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Monton, Capt. Harvey (?): ALS (torn), 1922 Aug (Box 1)
    - Morris, [Augustus] Newbold (1902-, Yale 1925): ANS, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Myers, William Starr: 2 TLS, 1917-1922 (Box 1)
    - Norton, William Bunnell (1905-, Yale 1925): 1 ALS, 1925 Jul 12 (Box 1)
    - Oliver, Marshal Leslie (1904-, Yale 1925): 1 ALS, 1925 Jun 30 (Box 1)
    - Osborn, Robert Chesley (1904-, Yale 1928): 2 ALS, 1928 Nov 2-11 (Box 1)
    - Philips, Eliza Irwin (Laughlin), Mrs Duncan Clinch Philips ("Little Aunt Lizzie") (?): 1 ALS, n.y. Jul 20 (Box 1)
    - Pitt, Nellie N.: 1 ALS, 1917 Feb 9 (Box 1)
    - Pierson, George Wilson (1904-, Yale 1926): 1 Card, 1932 Oct 29 (Box 1)
    - Poincaré, Raymond (1860-1934): 1 ANS, 1921 Aug 19 (Box 1)
    - Preston, Walter G., Jr.: 1 TLS, 1925 Mar 5 (Box 1)
    - Priest, George M.: 1 Card, 1 TLS, 3 ALS, 1918-1926 (Box 1)
    - Princeton University Endowment Fund, S. McKean Bayard: 2 TLS, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Reazor, Frank B.: 1 ALS, 1928 Nov 6 (Box 1)
    - Rébellian, Alfred: 1 ALS, 1921 Aug 5; visiting card; draft of reply (Box 1)
    - Root, Robert Kilburn (1877-1950, Yale 1898): 3 ALS, 1 TLS, 1918-1922 (Box 1)
    - Roseboro, Francis B.: 1 ALS, 1918 Aug 9 (Box 1)
    - [?S_______], Winthrop: 1 ALS, n.d. (Box 1)
    - St. John, Fordyce B.: 1 TLS, 1922 May 6 (Box 1)
    - Scranton, Charles W., Co.: Account, 1921 May 20 (Box 1)
    - Sewanee Review, George Herbert Clarke: 2 TLS, 1921 Apr 16, 1922 Apr 28, 1 carbon reply (Box 1)
    - Seymour, Charles (1885-, Yale 1908): 3 TLS, 1 ALS, 1923-1924 (Box 1)
    - Shipman, Frank Robinson (1863-, Yale 1885): 1 TLS, 1924 Mar 4, carbon reply (Box 1)
    - Shipman, Harvy Robinson (1877-, Yale 1899): 1 ALS, 1926 Nov 21 (Box 1)
    - Simon, Henry: 1 ALS (with envelope), 1921 Aug 11, draft & reply (Box 1)
    - Sorbonne (Université de Paris): Letter, card, draft reply, 1910 (Box 1)
    - Southern New England Telephone Co.: TLS, 1921 Sep 9 (Box 1)
    - Stanton, Theodore (1851-1925): 2 cards, 1921; draft reply (Box 1)
    - Terrell, James Mason (1900-, Yale 1923): 1 card (Box 1)
    - Tiblits, E. D.: 2 ALS, 1922 Apr 8, 1924 Aug 12 (Box 1)
    - Tighe, Richard Lodge (1902-1938, Yale 1923): 5 ALS, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster (1876-, Yale 1899): 8 ALS 1921-1925 (Box 1)
    - Troxell, Gilbert McCoy (1893-, Yale 1916): 6 ALS, 1 TLS, 1921 (Box 1)
    - Van Keuren, Frank E.: 1 TLS, 1922 Sep 26 (Box 1)
    - Van Winkle, Courtlandt: 5 ALS, 1921-1923 (Box 1)
    - West, Andrew Fleming (1853-): 1 TLS, 1910 Sep 22 (Box 1)
    - Westerfeldt, Mary: 1 ALS, 1918 Jun 28 (Box 1)
    - White, Paul Lambert (1890-1922): 2 ALS, 1921-1922 (with material from Helen Van Keuren White, Lazene L. White, Allen Johnson, and Andrew Keogh) (Box 1)
    - Williams, Robert: ALS, 1923 Oct 11 (Box 1)
    - Wood, N.: ALS, 1921 Jul 21 (Box 1)
    - Wyeth, John: Telegram, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Yale University: 6 letters from several departments (Box 1)
  - One folder labelled "General, and Unidentified," containing four miscellaneous pieces. (Box 1)
  - One folder entitled "Army Student Training Program, Foreign Area Studies and Records." (Box 1)
  - One folder of miscellaneous correspondence and notes:
    - Cartoon entitled "The New Yale" (Box 1)
    - Bragdon, Henry W.: notes on Woodrow Wilson's connection with Yale (Box 1)
    - Bragdon, Henry W.: ALS, 1942 Apr 12 (Box 1)
    - Hemingway, S. B.: ALS, 1944 Jan 29, clipped to handwritten notes of Professor Allison (Box 1)
    - Handwritten copy of letter of 19-Jul 21, to Harry [?] (Box 1)
    - Schedule with notes re: College Ply for Professor Allison, 1942 Mar 24 (Box 1)
    - [Removed and catalogued] Deane Keller's "American Impressions of Italians and Italian customs" - mimeographed (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Margaret Bailey (Laughlin) Allison Marshall [still in envelopes--re: school, travel, WWI] (Box 2)
  - Student papers: "There is No Caviar," by T.S. Paul; "The Influence of St. Francis in the XII and XIV Centuries," by Richard Duncan Gatewood; and an unidentified MSS on the Middle Ages (Box 3)
  - Two loose-leaf scrapbooks that originally contained letters now in box 6, with translations of some of the letters in Allison's hand (Box 4)
  - Army and Army Reserve: Correspondence and records; Army Reserve papers: correspondence and records, 1918-1922 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified correspondence and papers (Box 5)
  - Printed Materials: Lawrenceville, Princeton; Reviews of Thiers and the French Monarchy (Box 5)
  - Guillaume-Chrétien de Lamoignon de Malesherbes, 1758-1794
    - Longhand and typewritten copies of a critical note by Malesherbes on Montesquieu, June 25, 1767 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Typewritten and longhand copies of list of changes demanded by Malesherbe in Diderot's Pere de Famille, Circa 1758 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Typewritten and longhand copies of elisions, in Malesherbes hand, to Diderot's Pere de Famille, Circa 1758 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Facsimile of autographed letter signed from Malesherbes to an unnamed correspondent, June 18, 1786 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Copy of letter dictated to Hue on the last days of Louis XVI, Circa 1794 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Letters, Circa 1774 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes two copies of a letter regarding the freedom of the press
    - Copies of ten letters to and from Malesherbes or to his contemporaries, 1771-1787 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Signed letter to M. Thouin, March 9, 1789 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Note in Malesherbe's hand, probably regarding revisions he wished made in some author's manuscript before he would authorize its printing, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Epigraph, in Malesherbe's handwriting, for M. de Condamne, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Signed, autographed letter from Malesherbes to M. de Forebonais, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Signed, autographed letter from Malesherbes to unnamed correspondent, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Typewritten copy of a memorandum by Malesherbes on the coming meeting of the Estates General, 1789 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript copy of a discourse prepared by Malesherbes for St. Martin's Day, 1789 on the character of the French magistracy (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Account of an uprising at Limoges, probably written for Malesherbes, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Malesherbes' Observations on his exile and on M. Rene Nicholas de Maupeou, Circa 1771 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript copy of Malesherbes' discourse on the decline of discipline and dangers of unbridled independence among the magistrates, August 8, 1787 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Malesherbes to unnamed correspndents, 1759-1772 (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
    - Letter to M. de Boisgibault, October 28, 1769 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Letter to the Marechal de Noailles, April 17, 1776 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Signed letter to M. de Louvois, February 6, 1781 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Signed letter to unnamed correspondent, his nephew, December 19, 1787 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Signed, autographed letter from M. Chouart to Malesherbes, November 15, 1771 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Signed letter from Murine to M. Le Brun concerning property bought by Malesherbes, August 26, 1776 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Signed, autographed letter from L. de Barbancais to unnamed correspondent, declining to subscribe to a subscription for a memorial to Malsherbes, August 8, 1819 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Engravings of Malsherbes, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - General and collected correspondence
    - Allison, J.M.S.: Copies of letters to Pierre Cot, 1941 June 9 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Allison, J.M.S.: Copies of letters to Georges Andrieux, 1937 October 6; 1937 November 6 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Andrieux, Georges (auctioneer, Paris): signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1937 October 22 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Ashburn, Frank Davis (1903-): Mimeographed circular letter to Allison, with enclosure, 1942 October 9 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Aubert, Marcel (director of the Societé Francaise d'Archéologie), signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1938 May 20 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Barbarançois, L. de (pres. de la société d'agriculture du dépt. de l'Indre): signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, 1819 August 8 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Benjamin, Mary A.: 2 signed, autographed letter to Julia C. Hunt, 1941 June 5 - 1941 June 9 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Blanc, Louis (Jean Joseph Charles Louis, 1811-1882): signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, 1845 September 20 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Cavaignac, Louis Eugene (1802-1857): signed, autographed letter to Col. Roche, 1846 December 25 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Champsaur, Albert (hotel proprietor): signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1936 July 29 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Chapman, Marthe: signed, autographed letter to Allison, n.y. February 16 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Choart: signed, autographed letter to Malesherbes, 1771 November 15 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Cohen, Gustave (1879-): TLS to Allison, 1943 May 21 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Cot, Pierre (1895-): signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1941 June 5 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Diderot, Denis (1713-1784): 2 copies, 1 longhand, one typed, of letter to Malesherbes., 1758 October 20 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Diderot, Denis (1713-1784): Copy of a letter to the Princess of Nassau-Saarbruck, Circa 1758 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Donaldson, Norman V.: TLS to Allison, 1938 April 18, 1938 June 13 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Dosne, Félicie (1823-1906): Copies of two letters to an unnamed correspondent, 1870 August 20; 1871 January 1 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Fernand-Laurent, Camille Jean (1889-): TLS to Henri Peyre, 1943 October 7 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Filleul, Paul: 4 signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1936 July 29, October 17, November 29; n.y. October 22 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Focillon, Henri (1881-): 8 signed, autographed letters to Allison:, 1936-1940 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      General note
      The dates of these letters are 1936 Jul 1, Dec 13; 1938 Mar 10, May 20; 1939 Feb 21, Apr 22, Sep 27; and 1940 Mar 2
    - Focillon, Henri and Marguerite: signed, autographed letter to Allison, in handwriting of Henri Focillon, n.y. October 12 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Focillon, Marguerite: signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1936 July 1 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Ganay, Comte Ernest de (1880-): signed, autographed letter to Allison, with envelope, 1932 February 22 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Guizot, François Pierre Guillaume (1787-1874):
      - Signed, autographed letter to Jean Henri Grandpierre, 1863 November 30 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Signed, autographed letter to Tony Johannot, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - 6 signed, autographed letters to unnamed correspondents, 1838 May 12, 1844 December 10, 1847 October 24 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - untitled, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Receipt to unnamed person, 1818 August 29 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Knollenberg, Bernhard: TLS to Allison, with enclosure, 1941 April 29 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Koteliansky, Samuel Solomonovitch (1880-): signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, 1924 November 14 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Lamartine, Alphonse Marie Louis de (1790-1869): signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, 1847 January 27 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Lamoignon, Charles de: signed, autographed letter to M. Carieux, 1812 September 6 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Lamoignon, Charles de: signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent [the prefect of a dept.], 1809 September 16 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Louis Philippe, King of the French (1773-1850): signed letter to unnamed correspondent, countersigned by Molé, 1837 May 25 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Maroselli, A. (Senator): TLS to Henri Peyre, 1943 October 11 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Maurepas, Jean Frédéric Phelypeaux, Comte de (1701-1781): Typewritten copy of letter to unnamed correspondent [may be Malesherbes], undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Montesquiou, Abbé de [probably Abbé François de Montesquiou-Fézensac, 1756-1832]: Autograph of (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Périer, Casimir Pierre (1777-1832): signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, 1831 July 6 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Peyre, Henri (1901-): Copy of typed letter to Camille Jean Fernand-Laurent, 1943 October 11 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Rémusat [Comtesse de Claire Elisabeth Jeanne Gravier de Vergennes, 1780-1821]?: signed, autographed letter to Mme. de la Ferte, 1799 July 26 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Rémusat, Francois Marie Charles, comte de (1797-1875):
      - Signed, autographed letter to Marron [?], circa 1838 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - Signed, autographed letter to the editor of Moniteur, 1845 March 10 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - Signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, circa 1830 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - Signed, autographed letter to unnamed correspondent, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Ruffey, Mme. la presidente de: Copy of letter to Malesherbes [filed under 1771 Mar 24], 1776 February 27 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - St. Leger, --: signed, autographed letter to M. Bernardini, written on front of printed notice of subscription to be taken for the sale of a portrait of Malesherbes, 1826 December 13 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Sophia Christina Charlotte, princess of Nassau-Saarbruck:
      - 2 copies of 2 letters to Denis Diderot, 1758 October 28, November 15 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - 2 copies of letter to Baron Frederick Melchior Grimm, circa 1758 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - 2 copies of letter to Ludwig de Nassau-Saarbruck, 1758 November 15 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Sevin, André: signed, autographed letter to Allison, 1936 May 1 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - de Sers, O.: signed, autographed letter to Allison, n.y. February 9 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, Prince de Bénévent (1754-1838): Promissory note of, signed, 1838 August 1 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Tocqueville, Alexis Charles Henri Clerel de (1805-1859): Typewritten copy of letter to M. Sumner, with envelope, 1848 October 14 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Tocqueville, Jean, comte de: 3 signed, autographed letters to Allison, 1937 July 10, September 20; 1938 June 18 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Tocqueville [first name undecipherable, mother of Jean, Comte de Tocqueville]: 3 signed, autographed letters to Allison, 1938 August 11, 16; 1939 April 16 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Vercel, Roger (1894-): Signed, autographed letter to Allison, n.y. April 14 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Thiers, Adolphe (1797-1877):
      - Signed, autographed letter to M. Bogler, sculptor, with envelope, 1836 or 1848 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - Copies of 2 letters to M. Chopart, 1848 March 8, 1848 May 3 (Box 6, Folder 31)